<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">


<section id="config.pathparams">
	<title>Add Path-parameters to your mapped URL (REST)</title>
	<para>
		Suppose we want to create a URL mapping that allows users to access items in a  specific category
		of a web-store, such as: <literal>/store/category/</literal>. In other words, we want to take a piece
		of the URL string itself - for example: <literal>/store/[category]/</literal> and use that value: 
		<literal>[category]</literal> in our application's logic.
	</para>	
		
	<para>
		This is commonly known as creating a REST-ful URL, but here we'll use the term "path-parameter"
		to represent each individual data element created in our URL path.
		
		<tip>
			<para>
				Path-parameters are defined by using #{...} expressions in the pattern element. By default, 
				these expressions match any character except for '/' in a URL. So the following pattern
				will match <literal>/foo/</literal>, but it will not match <literal>/foo/bar/</literal>.
				
				<programlisting><![CDATA[<pattern value="/#{ name }/" />]]></programlisting>
				
				More specifically, path-parameter expressions such as <literal>#{ name }</literal> are replaced with the
				regular expression <literal>[^/]+</literal> before being matched against the URL. 
				<link linkend="config.pathparams.regex">Custom regular expressions</link> can also be supplied
				if more control over parameter matching is required.
			</para>
		</tip>
		
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<url-mapping id="viewCategory">
  <pattern value="/store/#{ cat }/" />
  <view-id value="/faces/shop/store.jsf" /> 
</url-mapping>]]></programlisting>
	
		Here we've used PrettyFaces path-parameter syntax to capture values stored in part of inbound URLs
		that match our pattern. Take, for instance, the following URL:
		
		<programlisting>/store/shoes/</programlisting>
		
		Part of this URL will be matched by the path-parameter expression: '#{ cat }',
		making its value, 'shoes', available in the application logic, the rest of the URL will be matched
		against the pattern, but ignored.
		
		<programlisting><![CDATA[<pattern value="/store/#{ cat }/" />]]></programlisting>
		
		The application can gain access to these path-parameters in a few ways, via 
		<link linkend="config.pathparams.named"> request parameter naming</link>, or 
		<link linkend="config.pathparams.el">EL bean injection</link>; both techniques will be covered 
		below.
	</para>
	
	<section id="config.pathparams.named">
		<title>Named path parameters</title>
		<para>
			In order to gain access to a value matched by our path-parameter <literal>#{...}</literal>, 
			we can use the named path-parameter syntax: <literal>#{ cat }</literal>, 
			which means that the value in the URL will be available in the HTTP Servlet request parameter map:
			<literal>HttpServletRequest.getParameter(String name); stored in the key 'cat'.</literal>
		</para>
		<para>
			In our application code, we would access the URL just like we access request query-parameters, 
			e.g.: <literal>url?cat=value</literal> , where 'cat' is the key, and 'value' is the value.
			
			<programlisting>String category = request.getParameter("cat");</programlisting>
			
			You could also use JSF 2.0 meta-data 
			<ulink url="https://javaserverfaces.dev.java.net/nonav/docs/2.0/pdldocs/facelets/f/viewParam.html">
			view-parameters</ulink> to propagate the named request parameter value to EL.
		</para>
		
		<tip>
			<para>
				If you are adding PrettyFaces to an existing web-application, it is very likely that
				you will want to use named path-parameters in order to tie in to existing application
				features.
			</para>
			<para>
				When starting a new application, it is good practice to always include a name for
				each path-parameter, even if you are using <link linkend="config.pathparams.el">EL bean
				injection</link> as well.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</section>
	
	<section id="config.pathparams.el">
		<title>* EL-injected path parameters</title>
		<para>
			Another method of accessing path-parameter values is via EL value injection, where PrettyFaces
			can	inject the value of the URL parameter directly into a managed-bean. This requires a
			syntax similar to specifying a named parameter, but PrettyFaces looks for '.' characters, an
			easy way to distinguish a name from an EL value-injection expression:
			
			<programlisting><![CDATA[<pattern value="/store/#{ bean.category }/" />]]></programlisting>
			
			In this case, we must have a managed bean defined in our application; these beans can be 
			registered either in JSF, Spring, Google Guice, or as shown here using CDI/Weld. Based on the
			configuration in this particular example, the bean must be named "bean", and must have
			an accessible field named "category". 
		</para>
		<para>
			Any value matched by the path-parameter will be injected directly into the bean.

<programlisting>@Named("bean")
@RequestScoped
public class CategoryBean {
	private String category;
	
	/* Getters &amp; Setters */
}</programlisting>
	
		</para>
		
		<tip>
			<para>
				Notice, you can specify both a name and an EL value-injection for the same path-parameter.
				
				<programlisting><![CDATA[<pattern value="/store/#{ cat : bean.category }/" />]]></programlisting>
		  	</para>
		</tip>
		
		<para>
			
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="config.pathparams.regex">
		<title>Restrict what Path Parameters will accept (Custom regex patterns)</title>
		<para>
			In PrettyFaces, each url-pattern compiles into a regular expression that is used to match incoming
			URLs. By default, any path-parameter expressions 
			(<literal>#{...}</literal>) found in the URL pattern will be compiled into the regular expression:
			<literal>[^/]+</literal>, meaning that path-parameters do not match over the '/'
			character. 
		</para>
		<para>
			The time will come when you need to make a URL match more selectively, for instance, when you have two 
            URLs that share the same parameter order. Or perhaps you need to take a very complex URL and parse it
            more selectively (matching across multiple '/' characters, for instance.) It is in scenarios like these
			when you should consider using a custom regular expression within your url-mapping pattern.
		</para>
      <tip>
         <para>
            When using any escape sequences in a custom regular expression, be sure to "double-escape" the 
            backslash character '\', otherwise the pattern will not be properly compiled, just as you would in
            Java itself.
            
            For example, in order to match digits: "<literal>\d+</literal>", you would actually need to add an
            additional backslash, like so: "<literal>\\d+</literal>"
         </para>
      </tip>
		<para>
			Let's consider, for instance, that you are building a blog application, where the URLs: 
			<literal>/blog/2010/12/</literal> and <literal>/blog/lincoln/23/</literal> have the same number of
			parameters, but mean different things. One is going to display a list of articles from December 2010,
			and the other is going to display Lincoln's 23rd post. There has to be a way for the system to tell
			the two apart, and the answer is custum regex patterns.
		
			<programlisting><![CDATA[<url-mapping id="archives">
  <pattern value="/#{ /\\d{4}/ year }/#{ /\\d{2}/ month }/" />
  <view-id value="/faces/blog/archives.jsf" /> 
</url-mapping>]]></programlisting>

			This pattern specifies custom regular expressions for each path-parameter, the former must
			match exactly four digits (numbers 0-9), while the latter must match exactly two digits. In order to
			understand what this means, it might make sense to think of what the pattern would look like once
			it is compiled into a regular expression:
			
			<programlisting><![CDATA[/(\\d{4})/(\\d{2})/]]></programlisting> 
		</para>
         <para>
			Below we see how to map the second of our two example URLs.
		
			<programlisting><![CDATA[<url-mapping id="viewAuthorPost">
  <pattern value="/#{ /[a-z]+/ blogger }/#{ /\\d+/ postId }/" />
  <view-id value="/faces/blog/viewPost.jsf"/> 
</url-mapping>]]></programlisting>
			
			Notice that this compiled pattern looks somewhat different from the first example URL:
			
			<programlisting><![CDATA[/([a-z]+)/(\\d+)/]]></programlisting>
			
			This is how you can completely customize and parse complex URLs (even capture values that include
			the '/' character.) Any path-parameter expression can accept a <literal>/custom-regex/</literal>, but
			the custom regex must be placed before any name or EL injections.
		</para>
		
		<warning>
			<para>
				Using custom regular expressions can lead to very difficult trouble-shooting, and is only
				recommended in cases where basic path-parameter expressions are not sufficient. 
			</para>
		</warning>
		
		<para>
			Sometimes you might want PrettyFaces to inject path parameters only on GET requests.
			This could be the case if you inject path parameters into a view-scoped bean and want
			to change these values at a later time.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			You can use the <code>onPostback</code> attribute of <code>url-mapping</code> to specifiy 
			if values should be injected on postbacks. Please note that the default value of 
			the attribute is <code>true</code>.
		</para>
		
		<programlisting><![CDATA[<url-mapping id="viewCategory" onPostback="false">
  <pattern value="/store/#{ cat }/" />
  <view-id value="/faces/shop/store.jsf"/> 
</url-mapping>]]></programlisting>

		<warning>
			<para>
				Please note that the bean properties bound to path parameters must never be 
				<code>null</code> as they are required to build the URL for form postbacks. 
			</para>
		</warning>

	</section>
</section>
